Hi, it's Handy Andy Tech Tips here.
Well, imagine if you could get AI to
control your keyboard and mouse so that
you could automate tasks on your
computer. That's now possible through
what's called a computer use model like
Gemini 2.5, but the general concept is a
lot older than you might think. Back in
1992, you could use the macro recorder
application in Windows 3.1 to do
basically the same thing. The difference
was that you had to manually record a
sequence of events, for example, mouse
movements and clicks and key presses,
and then you could play them back at a
later date. But now, fast forward to
2026,
and with the new generation of AI
agents, you can simply type in a text
prompt asking them to do a specific
task, and they will send screenshots
back to the model, which will work out
the correct actions to undertake. It's a
very powerful capability and in this
video I'm going to show you how to use
the Gemini computer use preview to
autonomously browse the web. Now to get
up and running you'll need to install
and configure a few things. I'm going to
be using Windows. This will work on Mac
or Linux but the setup will look a
little bit different. So firstly make
sure that you have VS Code installed
because that's the IDE that we'll be
using. Next, install and configure Git
for source control. When you're going
through the setup, you can leave most of
the default options as they are, but
when it asks you to choose the default
editor, change it from Vim to VS Code.
Okay. Next, install Python, which will
allow us to run the main project. I use
the version in the Microsoft Store, but
you can also get an installer from the
Python website. You'll also need to
install NodeJS which is required for the
Playright browser testing framework that
we'll be using. Of course, links to the
websites for all of these tools can be
found in the video description along
with a link to the GitHub page for the
computer use preview repo which has
detailed instructions for setup. All
right, let's get started. I'm in VS Code
and I'm going to open a terminal window.
Then click on the plus button and choose
git bash. The first command I'm going to
enter is git clone. Then the URL of the
GitHub repo for the project and then the
name of a new folder I want to clone it
into which is Gemini browser demo. This
will download all the files that we need
into that folder. Okay, now it's done.
And I'm going to open the folder in VS
Code.
And then I'll click yes, I trust the
author. Now I'll reopen the bash
terminal uh because it got closed when I
open the project and I'll use the second
command which is python 3-m
venv.ve
venv. This basically creates a python
virtual environment where we can
configure certain things without
affecting the rest of our system. So
I'll run that. And now you can see that
we have av folder and then inside that
there is a scripts folder. If you're
using Mac or Linux, the scripts folder
might be called bin. But anyway, inside
it, there is a script called activate,
which we need to run. So, type
source.ve/cripts
or /bin if you're on Mac or Linux slash
activate.
Now, you'll know if it's run correctly
if you get a response back of env.
See that? It means that we've activated
the environment properly. Okay, time for
our next command, which is pip install-r
requirements.ext.
The requirements text file contains a
list of packages that need to be
installed in Python for this project to
work. And this command will go and grab
all of them. There's quite a few, so
we'll just wait for that to finish. When
all the packages are installed, we'll
need to set up playright. This is a
library that's used for automated
testing of websites, but mostly these
tests are written in JavaScript code.
We're going to let an agent control it
instead. So run npm init playright at
latest. It will then ask you a few
questions, but the default options
should work fine. When it's finished
installing, you should run playright
install-deeps
chrome and wait for that. And then after
that run playright install Chrome. And
of course it's saying that I've already
installed it because I was playing
around with this earlier. Okay. So the
final part of the setup is to get a
Gemini API key which allows the agent to
talk to the model. The best way to do
this is to sign up for a free trial of
Google Cloud at cloud.google.com.
The trial gives you a couple of hundred
of free credits which will last for 90
days. You will need to put in your
credit card details for verification,
but it won't actually charge you for
anything unless you later decide to
activate a full account. When you have
started your free trial, go to Google AI
Studio at a studio.google.com
and then click on the get API key link
down in the sidebar. You'll see a list
of keys that you currently have. There
will probably be a default one there
already, but I've created another one
just for this project. Now, in order for
the key to work properly with a computer
use model, the quot tier should be
listed as tier 1 or above. If it says
free tier, it won't work. So, you'll
need to click on the link to set up the
billing. And then you can configure the
payment method that you set up in Google
Cloud. Okay. So, once you have a tier
one key, click on the key link. And in
the dialogue that appears, you can copy
the long string of characters under the
API key heading. Now when you go back to
VS Code, you can enter the following
command. Export Gemini API key and then
in quotes paste that key that you just
copied.
Ph. After all of that, we're finally
done. So let's have some fun now, shall
we? I'll start by asking the agent to do
a simple Google search. So I'll type
this command python main.py-
d-query
and then in quotes go to Google and type
I love AI into the search box and then
we'll need to specify the environment to
use. So type d-envals
playright in quotes. And now let's see
what happens.
It's creating a session and oh the
Chrome browser just popped up.
And uh here we go. It very quickly typed
I love AI into the search box. Uh and
now we have a capture test. I guess it
really is correct. This time we are
using a robot to send the request. So um
I'll go back to VS Code and it says,
"Yeah, the AI is actually asking us for
help with the capture," which is quite
funny. [music] So I'll type yes, I wish
to proceed. And then I'll go back to the
browser
and it's asking me to select the squares
with the crosswalks. So I think that's
all of them. And I'm done with that. And
now we have our page of search results.
Not bad. You'll notice as well that the
browser is running in a sandbox
environment which means that it has a
fresh profile and I'm not logged into my
Google account or any other services.
This is good for security because it
means that the agent can't send any
weird emails on my behalf or buy a Rolex
on eBay or anything like that. Now, a
really cool thing is that in the
terminal, we get a running commentary on
everything that the agent is doing. So,
it describes its reasoning and then it
says what actions it's taken to achieve
the result. So, you can see in this
case, it says that it's clicked on a
particular area of the screen.
Okay, let's try something a bit more
complicated. I want it to go to YouTube
and find me a video of a funny golden
retriever.
So, it will open up the browser.
And [music] now it's going to YouTube.
No captures this time.
And then it types funny golden
retriever.
And here's some videos.
Okay. Well, it didn't open [music] any
particular video, just the search
results. but it still claims that it's
achieved the goal.
So, it works well with Google's own
services. But let's try something else.
The Australian Bureau of Meteorology
recently redesigned their website, and
it's been criticized for being quite
difficult to use, especially when it
comes to the rainar section. So, I'm
going to ask the agent to go to
bomb.gov.au
and show me the Sydney rainar. Let's see
how it goes. [music]
Okay. So, here's the browser.
Now, it's going to open the site. And
here it is.
Uh, it's not doing too much. So, I'll go
back to VS Code. And the agent claims
that there's a user consent dialogue. I
can't see one, but uh, anyway, I'll just
type yes, I wish to proceed. And then
I'll go back and uh I'll scroll down the
page a bit. And
[music]
ah here we go. It's gone to the rain
radar now and the weather maps section
and it's scrolled to the map. Now the
question is can it find Sydney on here?
Let's see.
Oops. It's zooming into South Australia.
>> [music]
>> right in the middle of South Australia
near Kuba Pey but Sydney is on the east
coast nowhere near there
so it seems to recognize its mistake now
and it's kind of zooming out again
and now it's scrolled back up to the top
of the page and it's probably going to
just search for the location instead
will
Yeah, there we go. Sydney.
So, there's a few options. Which will it
choose?
It wasn't happy with any of them, I
don't think. So, it back based on that.
And now it's typing it again.
So, choose the right one this time.
Oops. It's chosen Darlington, Sydney,
and there's no results for that one.
Hey, agent, just between you and me, I
would have chosen just regular Sydney.
Uh, New South Wales. All right.
Well, it's trying yet again.
And no, it looks like it's just given
up. Now, this is the best part. If we
scroll through the logs in the terminal,
we can see the model's internal
monologue as it tries to find the
correct radar and kind of fails. So, I
guess you could say that Gemini has
officially failed the Bureau of
Meteorology test.
Well, I hope you enjoyed learning about
computer use agents. They're definitely
fun to play around with, but I think you
need to stick to the safer options. For
example, I won't be trying out the
infamous open claw on my main system
anytime soon, but this Gemini computer
use preview seems harmless enough, which
is why I demoed it in this video.
Anyway, I'm Handy Andy and thanks for
watching. Please subscribe for more AI
tutorials.